Guide to the 'ʻAlī Kassār Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
ʻAlī Kassār papers
1918-2004
1918-1938
MS 1875
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
The papers are primarily comprised of text and scores from Egyptian comedy theater productions and correspondence regarding Kassār's professional career.
Kassār, ʻAlī, 1887-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by the Near East curator from Leila Bookshop, Cairo, Egypt, 2005.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Plays: Scores and text, 1918-1938. II. Plays: Scores only, 1937, n.d. III. Plays: Text only, n.d. IV. Professional and personal, 1930-2003, n.d. V. Videos, 2004, n.d.
Biographical / Historical
ʻAli Kassār was born on June 13,1887, in Cairo's old traditional neighborhood of al Sayyidah Zaynab. His original name was ʻAli Khalil Salim Ibrahim. At the beginning of his career in 1908, he worked for al-Zaynabi Acting Company. In 1916 he founded his first troupe under his own name at the Casino de Paris theater located in 'Imad al Din street. He played his very famous character "Uthman al-Barbari" for the first time in 1916 in the play entitled, "Hasan Abu ʻAli Sarak al-Mi'zah." He used this character in many of his plays to criticize the political situation in Egypt. He also worked with famous composers, including Sayyid Darwish, from 1919 until the latter's death in 1923. After that he worked with Zakariya Ahmad from 1924 to 1929. In 1950 he dismissed his band and started working for the public theater that was founded and managed by the government of Egypt.
ʻAli Kassār ̄is considered the founder of comedy theater not only in Egypt, but in the Arab world. He worked in the theater for about fifty years and performed in about thirty movies. He passed away on January 15, 1957, at al-Qasr al-ʻAyni Hospital in Cairo.
Scope and Contents
The Papers are primarily comprised of text and scores from Egyptian comedy theater productions and correspondence regarding Kassār's professional career.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository.
Actors -- Egypt; Kassār, ʻAlī, 1887-1957
- Plays: Scores and Text, 1918-1938; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged chronologically and within year alphabetically by author/translator, and withinauthor/translator alphabetically by title. Authors/translators who are unknown are placed at the end of files for specific years. Plays with no dates are arranged at the end of the series alphabetically by author/translator. The series includes plays in which KassÄr acted but did not write, and plays he both wrote and in which he acted. Folder titles include the name of the author/translator and the title of the play in quotation marks. Each file is comprised of text and a musical score.
  - 1918
    - Sidqi, Amin
      - "Ism allah 'alayh" (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "Mafish kidah" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1919
    - Sidqi, Amin
      - "Filfil" (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "Marhab" (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Wilissa" (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1920
    - Sidqi, Amin
      - "Ahlahum" (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Fihmuh" (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Rahit 'alayk" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1921
    - Sidqi, Amin, "Sit al-kul" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1922
    - Kamil, 'abd al-hamid, "Alhilal" (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sidqi, Amin, "Um arba'a wa ba'in" (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1923
    - Sidqi, Amin, "Al-intikhabat" (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1924
    - Sidqi, Amin
      - "Dawlah al-haz" (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - "Idini 'aqlak" (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1925
    - Khayri, badi', "Al-ghul" (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - al-Sayyid, Hamid, "Al-tanburah" (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Sidqi, Amin,"'Uthman haykhush dunyah" (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Author/translator unknown, "Ayna al-raja" (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1926
    - al-Babili, Ahmad, "28 yawm" (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Hamid, Badi', "Abu zu'ayzi'" (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - al-Sayyid, Hamid
      - "Al-karnaval" (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - "Nadi al-samar" (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 1927
    - Hamid, Badi', "Malikat al-jamal" (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Ibrahim, Zaki, "Ibn far'un" (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Kassār, 'Alī, "Al-matami'" (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Khayri, Badi', "Hilm wala 'ilm" (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - al-Sayyid, Hamid
      - "Al-sufur" (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - "Qafashtak" (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Author/translator unknown, "Al-prins al-saghir" (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - 1928
    - Hamid, Badi'
      - "Nasiha 'ala al-hamish" (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - "Al-sikritayr" (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Khayri, Badi'
      - "Ghayat al-muna" (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - "Al-kunuz" (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - "Qadi al-garam" (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - al-Sayyid, Hamid
      - "Al-sahir abu fasadah" (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - "Taqiyat al-ikhfah" (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Wali, Sayyid, "Ana 'arif wa inta 'arif" (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - 1929
    - Khayri, Badi', "Mafish minha" (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - al-Sayyid, Hamid
      - "Ibn al-umbashi" (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - "Tahunit al-hawa" (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Author/translator unknown, "Min fihum" (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - 1930
  - Fawzi, Ibrahim, "Al-amirah al-majhulah" (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - al-Sayyid, Hamid
      - "Ana wa ibn 'ammi" (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - "Fatih baghdad" (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Sidqi, Amin, "Al-dam yihin" (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Author/translator unknown, "Bint far'un" (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - 1931
    - Ibrahim, Zaki and Zaki al-sayyid, Ahmad, "Amer ibn al 'as" (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Shikri, muhammad
      - "Habayib" (Box 6, Folder 48)
      - "Saraqu al-sunduq ya muhammad" (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Sidqi, Amin
      - "Al-gharjariyah" (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - "Hamatak tihibak" (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Zaki al-sayyid, Ahammad, "Al-madinah al-mashurah" (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - 1932
    - Kassār, 'Alī, "Al-halawani" (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Khayri, Badi',"Kalam al-umara' tamam" (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Shikri, muhammad, "Al-shayatin" (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Sidqi, Amin, "Ana lak wa inta liya" (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Author/translator unknown, "Itla' fiha" (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - 1933
    - Hadad, Al-farid, "Barghut afandi" (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - al-Sayyid, Hamid, "Fuq linafsak" (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Shikri, muhammad, "Zaqin al-basha" (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Author/translator unknown
      - "Al-barbari al tayih" (Box 7, Folder 61)
      - "Bis bis" (Box 7, Folder 62)
      - "Al-janayni" (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - 1934
    - Ibrahim, Zaki, "Fawanis al gharam" (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Khayri, Badi'
      - "Hanit" (Box 7, Folder 65)
      - "Ya bint al- ayh" (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Shikri, muhammad, "Bint al-shahat" (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Author/translator unknown, "Halak bumbay" (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - 1935
    - Ibrahim, Zaki, "Kalimah fi widnak" (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Ibrahim, Zaki & Al-sayyid, Hamid, "Al-dunya bikhayr" (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Kassār, 'Alī, "Al-dar aman" (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - 1936
    - Shikri, muhammad, "Hayat al-barbari" (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - 1938
    - Shikri, muhammad, "Al-birima dunuh" (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - n.d.
    - Kassār, 'Alī
      - "Al-zawja al-salihah" (Box 8, Folder 74)
      - "Ila al-amam" (Box 8, Folder 75)
      - "Kan ya makan" (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Mursi, 'Abd al-halim, "'Aja'b al-zaman" (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Sidqi, Amin
      - "Bariah min al-rigalah" (Box 8, Folder 78)
      - "Sirano" (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Author/translator unknown
      - "Abu nawas" (Box 9, Folder 80)
      - "Al-amirah al-hindiyah" (Box 9, Folder 81)
      - "'Aris al-hana" (Box 9, Folder 82)
      - "Bita' al-zayt" (Box 9, Folder 83)
      - "Huwa inta" (Box 9, Folder 84)
      - "'Iu'a tibasbas" (Box 9, Folder 85)
      - "Khatam al-malayk" (Box 9, Folder 86)
      - "Misir al-hay" (Box 9, Folder 87)
      - "Sah al-nawm" (Box 9, Folder 88)
      - "Al-sayyad" (Box 9, Folder 89)
      - "Shaykh al-balad" (Box 9, Folder 90)
      - "Al-sindibad al-bahri" (Box 9, Folder 91)
      - "Al-ustadh halambuhah" (Box 9, Folder 92)
      - "Ya walid al-ayh" (Box 9, Folder 93)
      - "Zal al-shar" (Box 9, Folder 94)
- Plays: Scores Only, 1937, undated; Series II
  The series is arranged alphabetically by composer/translator, and within composer/translator, alphabetically by title. Scores for which the composer/translator are unknown are arranged at the end of the series, alphabetically by title. The files consist of scores only.
  - Ahmad, Zakariya
    - "Abu shaduf", undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Bawabit juha", undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "Imbratur zifti", undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Malikat al-ghabah, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Darwish, sayyid, "Al-barbari fi al-jaysh", undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Muhammad zaki ibrahim, Tamsir
    - "Al-bakashah", 1937 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Kulina fi al-hawa", 1937 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Sidqi, Amin, "'Ifrit al-niswan", undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Composer/translator unknown
    - "Bayt al-natash", undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - "Khayr inshallah", undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - "Shahir al-'asal", undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - "Al-shaykh 'uthman", undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - "Zabayin jahannam", undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Plays: Text Only, Series III
  The series is arranged alphabtically by title. Authors/translators and years of creation are unknown. The files consist only of text.
  - "Abu al-nawm", undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Alfu layla", undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "'Ajayib", undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Badir al-budur", undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Al-barbari fi al-hind", undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Bashayir al-sa'd", undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Al-bata al-'ajibah", undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Fi al-mishmish", undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Halal 'alayk", undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "Al-hamshari", undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - "Haris al-qasir", undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - "Isti'rad al-amir kharub", undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Isti'rad: jawz umi,al-sayatin,qatir al-nada", undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - "Kaptin hul", undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - "Khalli balak", undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - "Al-misamih karim", undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "Musta'jil jidan", undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - "Sahih ya tayzah", undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - "Shindi bindi", undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - "42 sit", undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - "Su' tafahum", undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - "Tab fawwat", undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - "Al-warith", undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - "Ya sidi ya sidi", undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - "Zahrit al khabazah", undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
- Professional and Personal, 1930-2003; Series IV
  - Correspondence [mostly re: fundraising], 1943-1989, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Contracts [re: hiring actors, renting theaters, etc.], 1934-1948 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Copyright [correspondence from translators], 1930-1938 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Books about Kassār
    - Ali al-kassar fi zaman 'imad al-din [by Majid al-kassar], 2003 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Barbari masir al-wahid [by Majid al-kassar], undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Videos, 2004, undated; Series V
  The series is comprised of videos of films in which ʻAlī Kassār acted. They are arranged alphabetically by title.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - 'Ala qad lihafak [PAL], undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Alfi laylah wa laylah [PAL], 2004 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Nur al -din wa al-baharah al thalathah [PAL], 2004 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Sallifni 3 junayh [PAL], 2004 (Box 14, Folder 4)